A Guide to the James Lee-Teagle Family Papers, 1808-1877
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
James Lee-Teagle Family Papers, 1808-1877.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 50.6
14 items.
Teagle Family.; James Lee, d. 1845.; Edward Teagle, Jr.; Edwin Teagle.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1950.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm M-1117.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Lee was a teacher in Williamsburg, Va. who attended the College of William and Mary. He was the uncle of Edwin and Edward Teagle, Jr. of Williamsburg. Edwin Teagle was a sailor. He had studied under his uncle, James Lee.
Scope and Content Information
Family letters and papers of James Lee (d. 1845) and his nephews, Edwin (1812-ante 1839), William (b. 1815), and Frederick, the sons of Lee's brother-in-law, Edward Teagle, all of Williamsburg, Va. Collection includes a religious exhortation from Edwin to his father, an answer from Gilbert Cassard of Baltimore to Edwin's request to marry his daughter, and a letter from Edwin regarding the settlement of his father's estate and his projected travels to North Africa. In addition there are recommendations of Edward Teagle as an accountant or clerk, signed by Dabney Browne, Richard Coke, Jr., R. McCandlish, John Page, and Robert Saunders; various accounts; and a notebook of miscellaneous notes in French and long lists of clothes and household linens.
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Teagle family.
Persons:
Browne, Dabney.; Cassard, Gilbert.; Coke, Richard, 1790-1851.; Lee, James, d. 1845.; McCandlish, Robert, d. 1859 or 60.; Page, John.; Saunders, Robert, 1805- 1869.; Teagle, Edward, d. 1833Jr.; Teagle, Edward, Jr.; Teagle, Edwin.
Subjects:
African Americans-- Virginia.; Education--Virginia--Williamsburg.; Reconstruction-- Virginia.; Slavery- -Virginia.
Corporate Names:
George Reid House (Williamsburg, Va.)
Geographical Names:
Hampton (Va.); Morocco--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Morocco.
Contents List
- J. Lee, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Louisa C. Lee, Norfolk, 12 October 1808., 3 pages. (Folder 1)
  Concerns his intention to visit Norfolk, the sickness of his school children, a show at the Raleigh and other matters.
- John Page, Williamsburg to Edward Teagle, 12 September 1829., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Concerns Teagle's request for a letter of recommendation from Page.
- Account of Edward Teagle with James Lee, 23 September 1829., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Concerns the tuition of Edwin, William and Emiline Teagle, the children of Edward Teagle.
- Edwin A. Teagle, Portsmouth, to Edward Teagle, Williamsburg 26 September 1829., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Religious exhortation.
- Letters of recommendation for Edward Teagle from John Page, Dabney Browne, Robert McCandlish, James Lee, Robert Sanders, Richard Coke, Jr., 12-14 September 1829., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
- Gilbert Cassard, Baltimore, to Edwin A. Teagle, New York, 9 August 1835., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Cassard refuses permission for Teagle to marry his daughter.
- Incomplete letter, from Baltimore, to dear friend [Edwin A. Teagle?], 30 April 1836., 4 pages. (Folder 1)
  Concerns the weather and business in Baltimore and the possibility of internal improvements passing the Maryland legislature.
- Receipted account of the estate of Ed[ward A.] Teagle to Sheldon and Maupin, 27 July 1836., 1 page. (Folder 1)
- James Lee, Williamsburg, to Edwin A. Teagle, Baltimore, 2 August 1837., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Lee expresses his sympathy at hearing of Teagle's illness and informs Teagle of the death of his (James Lee) son.
- William Teagle, Staunton, to James Lee, Williamsburg, 1 April 1839., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Acknowleges receiving a deed from Lee for the George Reid House in Williamsburg.
- Frederick Bellett Teagle, Petersburg, to James Lee, Williamsburg, 16 February 1842., 2 pages. (Folder 1)
  Teagle asks Lee for spiritual advice and discusses his spiritual life. Asks whether the Superior Court commences in May or June.
- Jennie C. Thomson, Waverly, to Mrs. Mary E. Gilford, 5 February 1877., 4pages. (Folder 1)
  Discusses the marriage and the children of several old friends, the health of Mr. Telford. Writes that she is sad that Hampton "is overrun with negroes and Yankees ..."
- Edwin A. Teagle to Helen, ca. 1836., 1 page. (Folder 1)
  Teagle writes that he believes they are setting sail for Tangiers with "50 boxes (presents) for the Emperor of Morrocco." Also discusses his personal business.
- Notebook, 1817-1884., 53 leaves. (Folder 2)
  Contains notes in various hands in French and English. Includes lists of clothes and household linens; accounts concerning the hiring out of slaves by the day and the purchase of straw; and the selling of hen and duck eggs.